<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A president for a prince Wherein is to be seene by the testimonie of auncient writers, the duetie of kings, princes, and gouernours. Collected and gathered by Anthonie Russhe, Doctor of Diuinitie. Seene and allowed, according to the order appoynted.</title>
            <author>Rush, Anthony, 1537-1577.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1566</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11186</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116295</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851512</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851512</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16787</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11186)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16787)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 469:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A president for a prince Wherein is to be seene by the testimonie of auncient writers, the duetie of kings, princes, and gouernours. Collected and gathered by Anthonie Russhe, Doctor of Diuinitie. Seene and allowed, according to the order appoynted.</title>
                  <author>Rush, Anthony, 1537-1577.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By H. Denham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1566]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi²  A-N² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Duties --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16787:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16787:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PRESIDENT for a Prince. <hi>Wherein is to be ſeene <hi>by the teſtimonie of</hi> aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Writers, the duetie</hi> of Kings, Princes, and <hi>Gouernours.</hi> Collected and gathered by <hi>Anthonie Ruſshe, Doctor</hi> of Diuinitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seene and allowed, according to the order appoynted.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Sapient.</hi> 6.</bibl>
               <p>Ad vos nunc (O Reges) ſunt hij ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones mei, vt diſcatis ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, &amp; non excidatis.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vnto you now (O ye Kings) doe I ſpeake, that ye may learne wiſdome, and not go amyſse.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16787:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16787:2"/>
            <l>Quae breuiter paruo docuit pia Muſa libello,</l>
            <l>Conſilio formant Principis ingenium.</l>
            <l>Non tamen idcirco tibi ſunt dicata, quòd illis</l>
            <l>Indigeas, ſed quòd Principe digna ſient.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16787:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16787:3"/>
            <head>¶ TO THE MOST excellent and vertuous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe <hi>Elyzabeth, by the Grace of</hi> God Queene of Englande, Fraunce, <hi>and Irelande, defender of</hi> the Christian fayth. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>FPTOLOME Kinge of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, beyng exhorted by <hi>Demetrius Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lareus</hi> a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Orator, to buye Boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes endyted of Princelie proweſſe: for that he might reade therein thoſe leſſons, of the whych his friends or ſubiects durſt not put him in remembraunce: tooke that his counſell in very good parte, rendring thankes for that his gentle admonition, promiſing to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe his requeſt in that behalfe: the one
<pb facs="tcp:16787:4"/>
ſufficientlye aunſwering hys function in exhorting: the other in obeying and yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſame. I truſt your grace (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both wyſe and politike of your ſelfe, and therfore the leſſe lacking others meane and weake Aduertiſementes through the manifolde gyftes of your mirrored minde) wyll not miſlyke, if I of bounde duety, and preſt loyaltie, being youre humble and obedient Subiect (moſte puiſſaunt Princeſſe) ſhall wyth bowed breſt craue at your Maieſties hands, not the buying, or reading of all, or the moſt part of bookes written of gouernement, as <hi>Demetrius</hi> did of <hi>Ptolome:</hi> which were an endleſſe and an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite worke, (although not a very chargeable to a Kings or Princes cofers) but onely the acceptment and ſhielding of thys briefe Diarie and ſmall Manuell, and that wyth humble heart freely offred and behyghted (although groſſely and rudely pende: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altogether vnworthy of ſale, much leſſe of gift) to ſuche a Portly and puiſſant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage. In the which your Maieſtie may reade ſuche leſſons, not only to ciuill, but alſo to heauenly policie and practiſe dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as I (being a very blunt and vnskilful Oratour) eyther for want of audacitie, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:16787:4"/>
not be able before your dreadfull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to vtter and ſet forth, or your grace through magnanimitie and loftyneſſe of minde, ſhall of them in good part, after my meaning, not voucheſafe to conceyue: Dumbe and dead letters ſtanding in no awe or note of baſhfulneſſe, preſenting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues freely and frankly, wythout any copie, or chaunge of color: preſt perſons and humble ſubiects through weakneſſe of mind, &amp; bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning courage, at the preſence of the Prince trembling and quaking, and in diſcharging their tale ſtumbling and ſtaying. For when as to meane perſons ſome treatiſe and tenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of learning is dedicated, a preſent palme of vnfeyned frendſhip is openly teſtified, a ſhielder and ſuccourer of ſtudious trauels is obtayned, the renowmed fame of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone to immortalitie is commended: then moſt chiefly doth the humble hoſtage of louing loyaltie in ſubiectes appeare, when as to a Prince the like is preſented (who is in ſtede of an holie Anchor to all learned and skilful enterpriſes) when as partly they witneſſe them ſelues to be greatly indebted to his royall eſtate, partly alſo by ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion he is allured to the ſtudy of wiſdom. By which meane that taketh place, which
<pb facs="tcp:16787:5"/>
               <hi>Plato</hi> pronounced of all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weales, euen then they obteyning moſte bleſſed eſtate, when as eyther Princes were occupied in wiſedome, or the Profeſſors thereof were exerciſed in ciuil gouernment. For if a wiſe Prince bee called in the Scripture,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sap.</hi> 6.</note> the ſtrenthning of the people, and the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie cauſe and meane why Cities without any deſpeirment of ruine, be plenteouſlye inhabited, and farced wyth Citizens: it ſhall by them moſt plainely appeare, howe wel &amp; wiſely <hi>Plato</hi> wrote, placing wiſdome, the ſtudie of Princes. Which trauell all way bleſſedneſſe doth proſecute, as the ſhadow vnſeparably purſueth the bodye: I meane not the ſtudy of worldly wilineſſe, but of the wiſedome of God, vnto the which the holie Scriptures direct all redoubted Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Rulers of Kingdoms, euen by the voyce of the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſoundyng in their eares: <hi>Erudimini qui iudicatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Serni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Domino in timore.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.</note> Be ye learned you which iudge the earth. Serue the Lord with trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling feare. And not by his ſole &amp; only mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but by the direction alſo of Salomon his ſonne, a moſt perfect mirror of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie knowledge. If you delyte in ſeates and ſcepters,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sap.</hi> 6.</note> (O ye Kings &amp; Princes) loue you
<pb facs="tcp:16787:5"/>
wiſdome. For vnto you (ſayth he) O Kings, my words be wholy tendered, that you with meeting armes, embrace Gods truth and wyſedome, neuer goyng backe or reuolting from the ſame.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.</note> I nede not further preſſe the preachers learned leſſon: <hi>Diligite lumen ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae, omnes qui praeeſtis populis.</hi> Loue ye the large light of wyſdome, which gouerne and ouerſee the populous multitude.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> This light King <hi>Dauid</hi> called the worde of God, being a Lanterne to Princes feete, and a candle to theyr pathwayes. Thys light,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.</note> Prince <hi>Ioſeph</hi> plenteouſly publiſhed, inſtructing the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of Aegypt wyth doctrine, teaching hir Senators the wyſedome of God. May it therefore pleaſe your Maieſtie, to appoynt him as a paterne before your eies, that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row your heauenlie wyſdome and zeale of Chriſtian profeſſion, your Grace may be cleaped a Mother of Religion, as he was, a Father of the Kyng of Aegypt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 38.</note> a Nurſſe of Gods territorie and Church, as he was a foſterer, a ſhield to your ſubiects, as he was called a Sauiour of the world. Vouchſafe, O gracious Princeſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 26.</note> in naturall affection ad godlie pietie to folow <hi>Abimelech,</hi> who was daylie ſaluted of the <hi>Paleſtines,</hi> our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:16787:6"/>
the King: that your grace alſo may ſo be renowmed and accompted of vs your moſt louing and obedient children, our Mother the Queene: In defending your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes to aemulate <hi>Pharao,</hi> who was named of the Aegyptians, a reuenger of their iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: In Iuſtice to imitate <hi>Samuell</hi> or <hi>Aristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> In lofty courage to exceede <hi>Choelia</hi> and <hi>Portia,</hi> In liberalitie to aunſwere <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> In mekeneſſe to intercept <hi>Moyſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Adrian,</hi> In pacience, to forerunne <hi>Dauid</hi> or <hi>Ariſton.</hi> Then ſhall we iudge of your grace, as <hi>Italie</hi> did of <hi>Saturne,</hi> he purchaſing golden worldes vnto that fatall land. Then muſt wee (as no leſſe we can, through your bleſſed and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable gouernment) conceyue of your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, as the Romaines did of their Emperor <hi>Augustus,</hi> vaunting of him in thys ſort: <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam inuenit Lateritiam, reliquil Marmoream.</hi> He found Rome builded with tyle &amp; ſherd, he left it to vs made of Marble. Then ſhall we eſteeme thys Inſule, moſt happie, when as on your grace all eyes ſhall be fixed, as on a mirror or motion of wiſdome. Wherevnto (moſt dreadfull and Souueraigne Queene) I haue addreſſed the Methode of this booke, whych I haue dedicated vnto your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,
<pb facs="tcp:16787:6"/>
&amp; that vnder the title of, A Preſident for a Prince, for that moſt liuely (although ſuccinctly) it diſplayeth the whole race and courſe of Princely life, the order of his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the ſuppreſſement of loſe life, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe of forren enimies, a retinuing of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon peace, a naturall loue towardes hys ſubiectes, an earneſt zeale of Gods houſe, and to conclude, a true, faithfull, and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vſage of Chriſtes Sacraments, which S. Auguſtine calleth the viſible word, with all other good gyftes incident to a Princelie rule and prouince. Raiſe therefore (O moſt vertuous Princeſſe) according to your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed curteſie, at thys my humble and lowlie ſute, the ſitting ſayles of your noble heart, rechaſe the beawtifull balle of youre thronging thoughtes, enhaunce the earneſt allectiues of your ſtayed vnderſtanding, vnto the reading and peruſing hereof at your Graces lawfull leyſure. And to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, giue the prayſe, who ſowe in your moſt vertuous, and beſt meaning mynde, ſuch immortal ſeede of his heauenlie grace nowe in youre yong and flouryſhing age, that many yeares thys your Realme may enioy the plenteous fruite of thys hys bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb facs="tcp:16787:7"/>
in your royall perſonage, to the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie edification of hys Catholicke Church, and the continuall comforte of your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most humble Subiect and bounden Orator, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonie Ruſhe.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Haec tibi quae dabimus tenui conſuta libello,</l>
                  <l>Aspicienda oculis (caſta Diana) tuis:</l>
                  <l>Non te, quid deceat (cui ſunt ſua iura) docebunt,</l>
                  <l>Sed dedit hoc oneris, officioſus amor.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16787:7"/>
            <head>¶ A Preſident for a Prince.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was an auncient</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome among the Kings of <hi>Perſia,</hi> that very early eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning, of his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine comming to hys bed ſide, he ſhoulde be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened out of ſleepe, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted on this maner: Ariſe, O King, and loke to thy charge. Wherin may be wayed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe of their cuſtome, the diligence of the Chamberlaine, and the lowly obeyſance of the King to them both: To the cuſtome, for that it did ſet forth the nature of their lawe, wyth the equall power &amp; ſtrength of ciuile gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: To the Chamberlaine, for that he was made the Miniſter of this Meſſage, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie voyce of a dumbe conſtitution prepared to intercept &amp; preoccupate ydleneſſe wyth the ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of publike calamities, ſtrayghtly inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating meane reſt to be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for a Prince. No ſleepe permitted him in the day,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5.</note> as <hi>Strabo</hi> writeth, and great exployt and trauaile not to ſatiſfie a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale, yelding full relaxation to the body and minde, which are contented with moderate intermiſſion, by the night ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, preſcribing vnto the Citizens the whole courſe of the day, and that from the early mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb facs="tcp:16787:8"/>
wherby they the better might be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and by due execution of lawes, might be deteyned and kept in order. By the which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſement and ſage ſemblant, the <hi>Perſian</hi> Prince was put in minde (&amp; in him all others) not only of daily trauayle, but alſo of diligent expedition, incident to the office and Prouince of a Prince. Wherevnto nothing can be more preiudicial, than ſlouthfulneſſe, and more noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full than careleſſe ſecuritie (it being, as <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtocles</hi> ſayth <hi>Sepultura hominis viuentis,</hi> the graue of a liuing man) &amp; by the teſtimony of <hi>Marcus Portius,</hi> a iuſt purchaſe of the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Gods wrathful reuengement, being hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the body, vnprofitable to the minde, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paireful to publike policies, as both <hi>Plato</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>de Legib,</hi> &amp; <hi>Plutarch</hi> of <hi>Ageſilaus,</hi> do moſt plainly approue.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iliad.</hi> 2.</note> Wherefore <hi>Homere</hi> ſetteth forth ſleepe vnder the ſhape of <hi>Naeſtor</hi> commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning and talking with <hi>Agamemnon</hi> ſonne of <hi>Atreus</hi> chiefe Prince of Greece, wrapped in ſlouthfull ſlumber, ſharply rebuking him on this ſort: It becommeth not a Princely perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage (to whoſe gouernement the people be cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dited, in whoſe handes ſo weightie affaires of Domeſticall and forreine pollices be ſettled) to enioy one whole nightes reſt,<note place="margin">Sillius Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> according to this ſhort Poeſy: <hi>Turpe duci ſomno tota<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumere nocte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Neyther doth it lacke iuſt cauſe, that <hi>Virgil</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:16787:8"/>
his bookes of Martial proweſſe, and the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful feats of chaſing chiualrie, deſcribeth <hi>Eneas</hi> alway to be accompanied with faithful <hi>Acha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi> And <hi>Homere</hi> dyſplaying <hi>Pryamus</hi> famous factes, recordeth him to be attended vpon wyth olde <hi>Vcalegon,</hi> and auncient <hi>Antenor,</hi> who beare the ſeemelie ſhadowes of Kinglie cares. The which King <hi>Antigonus</hi> verified in hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe (and that with a vehement voyce) in thys wiſe aunſwering an olde woman whiche ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled his royal &amp; bleſſed eſtate: If thou knew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt (ſayd he) O auncient Matrone, how full of miſfortunes and thronging thoughtes this my Kingly Crowned and Diademe is farced, thou wouldeſt ſcarce vouchſafe to take vp the ſame from the ground. Wherfore wel may a Prince with <hi>Seneca</hi> ſay, and with <hi>Euripides</hi> confeſſe: <hi>Non curarum ſomnus domitor pectora ſoluit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Hecuba Trag. <hi>8.</hi> Se.</note> 
               <hi>ſemper nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mihi vigilant curae.</hi> Slepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tamer of toiles buildeth not in my breſt, cares do euery night watch and await on me. Wherfore, <hi>Chryſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> demaunded why he woulde not gouerne the common weale, aunſwered: If I gouerne it well, I ſhal be hated of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citizens, if I go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne it euill, I ſhal diſpleaſe the Gods. <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian</hi> was wont to ſaye, that nothing was more hard and difficult, than to gouerne well. <hi>Otho</hi> oftentimes aunſwered hys friendes: Beleue ye me, I had rather die than rule. Alſo
<pb facs="tcp:16787:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Antigonus</hi> confeſſed vnto his ſonne (and that euen of his carefull Kingdome) cleping it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, <hi>quàm ſeruitutem glorioſam,</hi> than a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious boaſting kinde of bondage. <hi>Solon</hi> deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribing Princes, noteth them to be nothing els <hi>quàm Miniſtros Seruos<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> multorum,</hi> than the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and Miniſters of many. <hi>Saturninus</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered his Complices intreating him to take Princelie place: <hi>Neſcitis, amici, quantum mali ſit imperare.</hi> You know not, my friendes, what a huge hurt it is to gouerne. Wyth the which perpetuall hatred is incorporated,<note place="margin">In Thebaid. Oedipo.</note> as <hi>Seneca</hi> writeth: <hi>Simul iſta mundi Conditor poſuit Deus: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Regnum. Odium qui nimium timet, reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare neſcit. Regna cuſtodit metus.</hi> God hath cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled gouernment and hatred together. He that feareth hatred is not mete to rule. <hi>Hieron</hi> the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore of <hi>Sicilie</hi> (as <hi>Xenophon</hi> writeth) ſayd, that pleaſures were more ſenſibly felt in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate life, than in the publike perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a Prince. Wherevnto <hi>Adrian</hi> and <hi>Domitian</hi> (as <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillus</hi> writeth) agree, confeſſing the eſtate of Kings to be moſt miſerable. <hi>Seneca</hi> clepeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame <hi>Poenam grauem,</hi> a grieuous puniſhment. <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> affirmed that two wayes being propoſed, the one leading to a Kingly throne, the other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducting to Hel: a wiſe man would preferre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> path, which leadeth to <hi>Pluto,</hi> before that which bringeth to Princely place. Of this
<pb facs="tcp:16787:9"/>
Prouince did <hi>Tiberius</hi> write in thys ſorte vnto the Senate: <hi>Quid ſcribam vobis P. C.? Quomodo ſcribam? aut quid omnino non ſcribam? Dijme Deae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> omnes perdant, <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> quotidie me perire ſentio.</hi> What ſhal I write vnto you, O you written fathers? How ſhal I write? Or what ſhal I not write at this preſent? Al the Goddes and Goddeſſes ſo deale with me, as I feele my ſelfe throughe cares daily dying. Wherfore, I can not better reſemble a Princelie eſtate, than to the rolling and reſtleſſe ſtone of <hi>Siſyphus,</hi> the ſtayleſſe whele of <hi>Ixion,</hi> and continuall gnawing and diſmembring of <hi>Tityus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Apolog.</note> it being (as <hi>Gregorie Nazianzene</hi> wryteth) <hi>Ars artium, &amp; diſciplina diſciplinarum, hominem regere, qui certè inter omnes animantes maximè est &amp; moribus varius, &amp; volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate diuerſus.</hi> The arte of artes, &amp; the diſcipline of diſciplines, to gouerne man, who among all lyuing creatures is moſt variable in maners, and vnconſtant in will. Furthermore, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a King (his combring cares ſet apart) is nothing elſe than a myrrour for all others to beholde (as <hi>Pindarus</hi> ſayth.) And as he beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth himſelfe, ſo are all others likewyſe affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. So that well may the Poet ſay:<note place="margin">Claud.</note> 
               <hi>Regis ad exemplar totus componitur orbis.</hi> And the common Prouerbe iuſtlie may be applied: <hi>Qualis Rex, talis grex.</hi> As the King is, ſo ſemblable are the
<pb facs="tcp:16787:10"/>
people humored:<note place="margin">De Lege.</note> who (as <hi>Tullie</hi> noteth) <hi>plus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplo nocent, <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> peccato,</hi> by example tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by offence doe more languiſh and annoy. Leaſt therefore Kings ſhould be vnmindefull of their carefull charge: the Auncient Paynims excited therto theyr Kings by outward enſignes and framed figures of vnreaſonable creatures, hauing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tops of theyr Scepters a Storke painted &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, in the end therof a ſea Horſe limned and arayed, to the end that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Storke they might remember to ſettle in theyr myndes pietie and godly loue (for the Storkes doe foſter the olde yeres of their Parents) by the ſea Horſe, fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and pride was ſhadowed, which Princes ought allwayes to ſubdue, and preſſe vnder their fete. And (as <hi>Pericles</hi> ſayth) not onely to haue chaſt handes, but continent eyes. I leaue to the field of forgetfulneſſe the people of <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. de Iſid.</note> who (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> writeth) had the pictures of their Princes and Iudges drawen and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neated without handes, and theyr eyes cloſed vp, for that Princes ought not to be allured with giftes, neyther perſuaded or counterpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with mens countenances: I might here ſpeake of the monument of King <hi>Simandius,</hi> in which the Prince and chiefe Iudge did ſit in the middeſt accompanied wyth .xxx. of the Nobles aſſiſting both his ſides: from whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:16787:10"/>
necke the picture of truth did hang downe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hir eyes ſhut, bending the ſame towards the breſt, for that a Prince ſhould be dailie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in the practiſe of truth. I conceale laſt of all the Egyptians: they of cuſtome putting about theyr Princes necke a Tablet embrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with diuers precious pearles, the which they called and cleaped, truth. What ſhoulde I ſpeak of famous <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedone?</hi> who accuſtomably was wont to ſay, that it behoued a King to remember, that he beyng a man, had atchieued heauenly power, and muſt put in vre honeſt and godly exploytes, and vſe ſoftneſſe of ſpeach towards his ſubiects. I paſſe ouer <hi>Agathon,</hi> who willeth a Prince to call to memorie three things: Firſt, that he hath go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment ouer men: Secondly, that he ought to rule according to lawes: Thirdlie, that he muſt not alway gouerne. For the Prince (as <hi>Tullie</hi> writeth) is a ſpeaking law:<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de leg.</note> and the law is a dumbe maſter. The end thereof is iuſtice and right, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> teacheth.<note place="margin">Ad imper. ducem.</note> The worke of the Prince is the law, and the Prince is the Image of God adminiſtring al things as <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere</hi> noteth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Odyſs.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Imago autem Rex est animata Dei.</hi> Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Calliope</hi> the moſt bewtiful of the nine Muſes doeth alwayes proſequute and accompany, as
<pb facs="tcp:16787:11"/>
               <hi>Heſiodus</hi> witneſſeth,<note place="margin">In Theo.</note> filling him with al hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly wiſdome, and pleaſant ſpeach. Whome all the people haue in admiracion. In whoſe bulked breſt <hi>Homere</hi> placeth fortitude and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: <hi>Tullie,</hi> abſtinence and continencie: <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius,</hi> lowlyneſſe in hearing, pleaſauntneſſe in anſwering, cunning artificiouſneſſe in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuading his ſubiects: whoſe royall eſtate <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Seuerus</hi> ſetteth not in outward pompe, but in inward vertues: <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> deſcriueth ſo to be affected, that with mercy he ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke offenders to repentaunce, and a full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoltment from lothſomneſſe of life. To whom <hi>Plato</hi> giueth two preceptes: firſt, that he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe his ſtudy to the profit of his ſubiectes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng an euerlaſting forgetfulneſſe of priuate profit and gaine: ſecondlie, that be ſo care for the whole common wealth, that in prouiding for one part, he ſeeme not to forſake and leaue ſuccourleſſe the other.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Offic.</hi>
               </note> Whoſe proper Prouince is to weigh that he beareth and ſuſteyneth the perſon of the whole Realme, euen as he were an <hi>Athlas,</hi> holding the high heauens vp with his ſhoulders, &amp; ſtayd ſtrength. Whoſe lawes he muſt kepe, whoſe rites and cuſtomes he muſt deſcriue, always mindefull of his portly place. Vnto the which wel ſerueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nander:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<pb facs="tcp:16787:11"/>
               <hi>Principatum aſſequutus, ſis hoc dignus.</hi> In whome both vtterance an wiſdome is required: vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, by the which he may praiſe famous and worthie men, he maye exhort to noble pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſſe, he may cal backe from hainous wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he may comfort the weake minded, and the noble enterpriſes of valiant warrefares, he maye commende to immortalitye: Wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by the which he may guide and gouerne his people, he may eſtablyſhe lawes, he maye puniſhe and correct offenders, and may defend and ſaue harmeleſſe iuſt and innocent perſons. Whom, <hi>Syrus</hi> preſcribeth not to be inferior in vnderſtanding thoſe things which be nedefull, than to gouerne as time and oportunity requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, whoſe perſonage &amp; trauaile in buſineſſe, courage in perill, diligence in working celeritie in accompliſhing, prouidence in foreheeding, ſingulerly ſetteth forth. Of whom anger is to be kept vnder, riot to be reſtrained, the ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of couetouſneſſe farre to be ſequeſtred, and all other deformities of minde vtterly to be exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, being ſo neceſſary an Organ, as withoute whom no Citie can be ſetteled, ſhewing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſtoute, iuſt, ſeuere, valiant, liberal, boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and meeke, withſtanding the fierceneſſe and inconſtancie of the monſtrous multitude, prouiding not only in his owne life for ſafe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignitie,
<pb facs="tcp:16787:12"/>
but in theirs alſo who ſhal ſuccede and gouerne after him,<note place="margin">In Lelio de Regno.</note> whom (as <hi>Dion</hi> wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) ſimplicitye and truth doth commend, and bring reuerence of all eſtates. Wherefore the Egyptians had their Kings in greate honor, iudging their gouernment to deſcend from the Goddes. And for this cauſe <hi>Neſtor</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Iliade</hi> of <hi>Homere</hi> warneth <hi>Achilles,</hi> that he make no countermaund with <hi>Agamemnon <hi>(cui princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patus à Ioue datus ſit)</hi>
               </hi> to whom Princely power was behighted of <hi>Iupiter.</hi> And <hi>Mynos</hi> King of <hi>Crete,</hi> the Poet calleth the familiar of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> who muſte haue no leſſe care of gouerning o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, than of himſelfe. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing more Princelike can happen,<note place="margin">Cicero in Para.</note> than vtterlye to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe all lothſome luſtes, and rather to bridle his owne immoderate affections, than to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn and preſſe his ciuile ſubiects. For (as <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> writeth) <hi>Non eſt cadentis currere, aut incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſiti componere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Ducem.</note> 
               <hi>aut parere neſcij imperare.</hi> It is not incident to him to run which falleth, or is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered to ſet in order, or voyde of obeyſance to gouerne and rule. Wherfore <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith: <hi>Si vis omnia tibi ſubijcere, ſubijce te rationi. Multos reges, ſi te ratio rexerit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſtola.</hi> 38.</note> If thou wilt ſubdue all things vnder thee, ſubdue thy ſelf. So ſhalt thou rule many, if reaſon rule thee. Whoſe honor is, not to be feared outwardlye of the people: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:16787:12"/>
when they with themſelues haue in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration hys mirrored minde, than his infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and fickle fortune. Wherefore all men (as <hi>Iſocrates</hi> writeth) iudged <hi>Euagoras</hi> Prince in Greece not ſo bounteouſly bleſſed for his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment ſake, as his Subiectes obeying the Princely power of ſo worthie a King. For he ſo ſpent the whole race of his life,<note place="margin">Iſo. in Eua.</note> that he hurte no man, and yet honorrd all good men: ruling diligentlye ouer all, and lawfullye puniſhing malefactours. Whome wiſedome maruelouſly adorneth, as <hi>Stenida</hi> teacheth:<note place="margin">Li. de regne.</note> for therof reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence iſſueth, and an emulation of the highe God, who by nature is the firſt King, and moſt Princely perſonage, but by creation and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Prince on earth. God is in all, aſwell in heauen as earth: and the Prince on the earth only, who truly treadeth in his ſteps, if he ſhew him ſelf couragious, wiſe, vnworthy of wicked worldlings, bearing in his breſt a fatherly mind towardes his ſubiectes. And (as <hi>Themiſtius</hi> writeth) a Prince in dede,<note place="margin">Xenophon lib. <hi>8.</hi> de Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Cyri.</note> in truth being inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnable, ſubduing his capacitie to reaſon, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing liberty, praiſing magnanimitie, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing &amp; aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>doning all ſtately ſtubbornneſſe. And therefore <hi>Ecphanta</hi> deſcriuing a King, ſayeth, that he is the excellent worke of God, his liuely image, familiar to his framer, gazed
<pb facs="tcp:16787:13"/>
on of his Subiects as it were an amaſing mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. For his worthineſſe is approued no other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe,<note place="margin">Stenidae ex lib. de reg.</note> than the Eagle is tried to be the Prince of birdes, his eyes openlie diſplayed againſt the ſunne. Wherevnto moſt like is a Princely go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, for that it is heauenly: throughe the ſurpaſſing cleareneſſe whereof, the eyes of thoſe who vniuſtly aſpire to Princelie prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are daſeled and blinded. Wherfore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth a Prince to make his gouernment ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by his maners. For ſo eftſones the ſame doth glitter and ſhine, vaunting it ſelfe wyth fluttering wings, whoſe portlie place, huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie greatlie enhaunceth, power pacifieth, knowledge confirmeth. For by knowledge he may iudge righteouſlie, by power he may pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe, by humanitie he maye largelye behight giftes, and according to reaſon adminiſter all things. In whom <hi>Diotog.</hi> coucheth three com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly qualities,<note place="margin">Lib. de reg.</note> and mirroring motions: the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of the Goddes: the gouerning of hys Subiectes: the iudging hurtleſſe and innocent perſons. Vnto the worſhipping of the Goddes he ſhalbe able, if he weigh with himſelf the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and power of God. To gouerne well, he ſhall be fit, if he vnderſtande the feates of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualry. To iudge and deciſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſies, he ſhal be cunning, if he haue diligentlie learned the
<pb facs="tcp:16787:13"/>
nature and courſe of Ciuil Lawes. <hi>Plato</hi> alſo in <hi>Protagora</hi> placeth in a Prince theſe three, not Portingale, but Precious pearles: <hi>Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, opinionem, ac loquendi libertate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Knowledge, good report, and ſwiftneſſe of toung. Who (of <hi>Ecphanta</hi> a Sectarie of <hi>Pithagoras</hi>) is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. properlie a Prince, of gouerning and ruling himſelf. And therfore <hi>Socrates</hi> calleth him the beſt Prince, which could beſt ſubdue and conquere his own affections, and muſtering motions. And <hi>Cato Maior</hi> counted him the worſt Prince: <hi>Qui im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perare ſibi ipſi nequiret.</hi> Who could not rule and gouerne himſelfe.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> de conſ. Honor.</note> For (as <hi>Claudianus</hi> wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) <hi>Tunc omnia iura tenebis, cùm poteris Rex eſſe tui.</hi> Then ſhalt thou beſt gouerne and preſcribe lawes, when thou canſt beſt rule and ſubdue thine owne ſelfe. Neither <hi>Iſocrates</hi> diſcenteth from the ſame, ſettyng forth the modeſtie of a Prince in ſtede of a mirrour or glaſſe to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, knowing the maners of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole Realm to grow like to the maners and conditions of the King. Wherfore <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayth:<note place="margin">In Thyeſte.</note> 
               <hi>Rex velit ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſta: nemo non eadem velit.</hi> The King exerciſing honeſtie, all men wil purſue the ſame. But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, <hi>Grauiſsimus eſt morbus qui à capite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funditur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Epiſtolis</note> It is the moſte daungerous diſeaſe, which diſtilleth from the head. Who muſt take
<pb facs="tcp:16787:14"/>
hede, whom he ſemeth to loue or defend. For he ſhalbe iudged like vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Demosth. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra And.</note> Whome alſo it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth to take dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reſpect of flatterers, and cacoglotting <hi>Coriſoes,</hi> by whoſe painted Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies Princes are abuſed, and they forced to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked enterpriſes. As wel it appeared in <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the great, who harkening to their flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring fables killed his true friendes <hi>Philota, Cliſthines,</hi> and <hi>Parmenio.</hi> Thus read we of <hi>Hieron</hi> throughe <hi>Epicharmus</hi> his Paraſite: The like teſtifieth <hi>Tranquillus</hi> of <hi>Domitian,</hi> and <hi>Amianus</hi> of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greate. Whom <hi>Homere</hi> calleth: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Ore benigna loquentes, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore praua ſtruentes.</hi> Faire ſpeakers with theyr toungs, but workers of wyckedneſſe in theyr heartes. And therfore <hi>Tullie</hi> calleth this ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned ſentence of <hi>Epicharmus: <hi>Memento diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</hi>
               </hi> be mindeful to miſtruſt: the very ſinewes &amp; marrow of wiſdome. Wherfore King <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonus</hi> in mirth was wont to ſaye, that he daily deſired of God, <hi>Vt ab eo etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aduerſus amicos pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegeretur.</hi> That he might be ſafegarded of him, euen againſt hys friendes. Theſe did <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> taſt of, euen by his own confeſſion in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like apparance of al his people: <hi>Ex hiſtorijs quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidie geſtis videmus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hester.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>quo modo malis quibuſdam ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtionibus Regum ſtudia depraue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur.</hi> Out of daily
<pb facs="tcp:16787:14"/>
Hiſtories &amp; Annuals (ſayth he) we may learne how that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godlye endeuours of Kings, by the wicked motions of flatterers be hindered and diſturbed. Neyther muſt he admit all men into his familiaritie, whiche couet and affectate the ſame, but ſuch onely as are worthy for his wit and diſpoſition: not thoſe with whome he may wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tonly waſt his flouriſhing yeres, but rather ſuch, by whoſe aduertiſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and cunning coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, he may beſt gouern and rule his Realme. Neyther muſt he count thoſe faithfull friends, which do proſecute with praiſe al his trauailes and talkes (as do Gnathonical &amp; ſnockfeaſting Paraſites, with men pleaſers, ſcrape ſleues, and trim time ſlaues, of the whiche great ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pluſage there is in all Realmes:) but rather thoſe,<note place="margin">Iſocrates.</note> whiche with modeſt maner rebuke &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine their inſcient errours. Vnto ſuch ought frankeneſſe of toung to be permitted, that of what matters he ſtand in doubt, by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may be reſolued and diſcharged from all ſuſpence &amp; ſcruple of minde. Applying his gouernement to the nature of his ſubiectes. With good men dealing moderatly, with ſluggardes veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with foole hardy folkes, ſharply, with warie and prouident men, wiſely and gentlie, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the counſell of <hi>Seneca,</hi> who ſayth:<note place="margin">In Thebaid.</note> 
               <hi>Qui vult regnare, languida regnet manu:</hi> who ſo wyll
<pb facs="tcp:16787:15"/>
gouerne, let him rule with humble hande. For like memory and fame ſhal he receiue, whether it be good or yll. Which thing well weighed, he hath free choyſe to enter which waye he will, eyther that which leadeth to infamie, or which conducted and piloceth to diſhonor, and that which ſemeth better to follow and purſue. For this is the peculiar profite of a Prince, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiualent with infinite others,<note place="margin">Euſebius.</note> in ſuch ſorte to ende and finiſhe all things, that not onelye in his life time, but euer after, throughe his vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe and godly gouernement, he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue immortall praiſe with the eternall teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and witneſſe of his ſubiects. The which <hi>Ouid</hi> opened in this ſort:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> de Ponto.</note> 
               <hi>Regia (crede mihi) res est ſuccurrere lapſis.</hi> And ſage <hi>Seneca</hi> ſemeth to confirme the ſame:<note place="margin">In Medea.</note> 
               <hi>Hoc Reges habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t magnificum &amp; ingens: Nulla ꝙ rapit dies prodeſſe miſeris.</hi> It is a Princelie vertue to helpe them who be fallen into aduerſitie. For this fortunate fact, immor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>talitie doeth alwayes proſecute. And therefore <hi>Euſebius</hi> reſembleth the rule of a King, vnto a man that hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the charge of a precious Iewell. For euen as he receyueth not the ſame to retaine it to his own priuate vſe, but to ſaue it, and alſo to deliuer it whole to his handes, who hath lefte the ſame in his credit, when he ſhall demaund it: ſo alſo ought a Prince, not
<pb facs="tcp:16787:15"/>
to his priuate gaine, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wealth &amp; commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of his ſubiectes, to apply his ſoueraigntie, ſo that harmleſſe and in happy eſtate (as much as lieth in him) he may both leaue and reſtore the people vnto God who firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his charge.<note place="margin">Li. An. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex.</note> The whiche (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) <hi>Pulcherrimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> funus conciliat,</hi> doth purchaſe a moſt bleſſed buriall, &amp; by the ſentence of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monides,</hi> doth ſtretch it ſelfe to all poſterities and ages. So that (as <hi>Bion</hi> ſayeth) he leauing his Kingdome, muſt rather ſeeke to dye glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie than furniſhed richelye. Whiche is (as <hi>Martialis</hi> writeth) to care and knowe his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes: <hi>Principis eſt virtus maxima noſſe ſuos:</hi> And <hi>Claudianus</hi> in this daintie Diſtichon, <hi>Tu ciuem patrem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> geris, tu conſule cunctis: Nec tibi, nec tua te moueant, ſed publica vota.</hi> It is a Princelye ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue to know hys ſubiects, and to prouide as a citizen and as a father for them all, his owne priuate gaine ſet a part. To whome moſt loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie ſubiectes doe giue, when as he not liuing wickedly, and yet ruling Imperiouſlye, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently doing thoſe things which appertaine to his office, offereth himſelf an example vnto them. For (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Poet teacheth) <hi>Non ſic inflectere ſenſus humanos Edicta valent, quàm vita regentis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Claudianus</note> Lawes are not ſo able to allure me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, as is the lyfe of the Prince. Wherefore
<pb facs="tcp:16787:16"/>
with the immortall ſtile of <hi>Plutarch</hi> is <hi>Ageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> behighted, who in all preſent enterpriſes and painful exigents to al his ſurlie ſouldiers, gaue the firſt aſſault &amp; outſet. Whereby they were animated and made bolde to battell.<note place="margin">In Lacon.</note> 
               <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras,</hi> alſo willeth Princes to ſtand in awe no more of others than of them ſelues, and to ſinne neuer the more,<note place="margin">Democritus</note> if no man ſhoulde know it, as if it ſhould be open to all men, but that he ſhould moſt chieflie feare himſelfe and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the lawe, not onelye of nature, but alſo of God in his minde. For his ſecrete faultes God himſelfe will diſcouer, both to his great appal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dreadfull example of others, who is not authorized to hurte,<note place="margin">Thucydi. ad Hemet.</note> but rather to helpe, being worthie of his gouernment, not through the gorgious eſtate of the common weale, but by the excellencie of vertue,<note place="margin">Epiſtola Sopa.</note> and mildeneſſe of minde. And thoſe of whom before he made no accompt, now preferred to Princelye place, he ought to reuerence and eſteme, and beholding all men his loyall louers, with a fatherly frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ought to embrace them. For vnto the <hi>Moe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Poet, it was not ſufficient to haue called a Prince, ſimply a Father (althoughe no more notable a name amongſt men coulde be found oute) but vnto the title of a Father he addeth his Epithete <hi>GENTLE:</hi> iudging this name
<pb facs="tcp:16787:16"/>
to Fathers and Kings moſte mete, ſitting and conuenient. To whom alſo it belongeth wyth moderate chaſtiſement to puniſh offenders, diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſembling ſmall and common faultes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing to ſubdue them by lawes, and (as <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chita</hi> ſayeth) to do all things for his ſubiects, &amp; nothing for himſelf. For the law alſo was not made for it ſelfe, but for the behoofe of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, whom he ought to promote to honeſt ſtudies, &amp; to giue to euerye one competent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrement, and to fill his Cities with all libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall learning, deſeruing well of his nobles and peeres, being bountifull in giftes, not with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall weight chaunging like for like, but plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly pouring them out of veſſelles, and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally diſpenſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the Poetes write. This maner of thankfulneſſe (ſaith <hi>Iamblicus) <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritò coronam Imperij appellauerim,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Iamblicus ad Dyſcoliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> I maye worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleape the crowne of Kingly gouernement. If therfore a King would conſecrate any noble and famous monument vnto hys Realme: let him decke and adorne himſelfe with the moſt precious and beawtifull ornament of meke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, iuſtice, and beneficence. So that in gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious building, Princely honor is not ſettled, but in courage of minde. For much more bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is, that hauty heartes ſhould dwel in pore and courſe Cotages, than that ſlauelike pages
<pb facs="tcp:16787:17"/>
ſhould lurke in loftie lodgings, and bountifull buildings, as it were ſauage beaſtes in a den. For neither with ſtones fette out of <hi>Euboea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epict.</note> nor with timber out of <hi>Sparta,</hi> is the Realme rayſed to honor, but with ſkilfull ſciences and louing liberalitie: <hi>Animis enim hommum, non la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidibus &amp; linguis bene habitantur Ciuitates.</hi> For by the pollicies and mindes of men not wyth ſtones and tounges are Cities peopled and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited. And as he is no good Horſe courſer, which only foſtereth the yong &amp; meke Colts, and leaueth the wilde hungry, and in perill of pining, when as he ſhoulde alike nouryſhe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, and ſhoulde make the one matche to the other: So ought a Prince well experienced, to belinke with benefites his good ſubiectes, and yet not to caſt away the euil,<note place="margin">Epictetus.</note> but to prouide in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently for them both: loſelye reigning the good, and ſharplye bitting the euill and ſauage ſubiect: And as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne loketh not for praiers and incantacions, that he may runne his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed courſe, but ſtraightwaye ſhineth with bright beames, &amp; is ſaluted of all men through the whole world: ſo ought Princes not to loke for the vncomelye clapping of the rude rables hands, and popular praiſes when they beſtow benefites, but frankly and freely to offer them. And ſo ſhall they bee beloued as the Sunne.
<pb facs="tcp:16787:17"/>
Who muſt aſſociate vnto him ſelfe reaſon, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowyng the ſame of the ſtudye of wiſedome, which hauing cuſtodie of hys minde, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is perillous in power (as it were in an incumbating habite) he maye withdrawe, in ſafetie leauing and yelding the ſame. Who by others muſte vſe compulſion and violence, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering offenders to bee puniſhed by inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. But when rewardes be tendered to ſuch as haue well deſerued them, he muſte then by his owne perſon deliuer and behight the ſame. Neuertheleſſe, they be not alwayes true Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which doe beare ſwordes and Scepters, to vſe outwarde force and violence, but thoſe (as <hi>Xenophon</hi> teacheth) doe we truely accompt Kings, <hi>Qui regere ſciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; iubere quid oporteat fieri.</hi> Which know how to rule, and to commaunde what is expedient to bee done. For theſe two can not agree together, as <hi>Lucanus</hi> writeth, the Prince bounde to execute Iuſtice, Scepters onelye regarding vnrighteouſneſſe. Whoſe whole ſtrength is vtterly languiſhed, <hi>Si pendere iuſta incipit,</hi> if he wey in his kingdome righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dealing: to wit, the puniſhing of malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, defending, &amp; rewarding faithful ſubiects. Wherevnto of bounde dutie he is belincked and preſt. For which cauſe <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> cleapeth him <hi>Cuſtodem legis,</hi> the keper of the law: <hi>Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pides</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16787:18"/>
deſcriueth him to be bountifull rewards men and a great friend. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Sit beneficus erga homines, &amp; magnus amicus. <hi>Ecphanta</hi>
               </hi> cleapeth a Prince <hi>Viuam le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem,</hi> a liuing law, which <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> calleth <hi>Ciuitatis animam,</hi> the ſoule or life of the Citie, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And ſtrayte way he addeth the Aetiologie therof. For as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body ſpoyled of the ſoule, doth faulter and fall, ſo the Citie is ouerthrowen, lawes being remoued. The lyke ſimilitude vſeth <hi>Tullie</hi> writing of lawes: <hi>Vt corpora noſtra ſine mente, ſic Ciuitas ſine lege, ſuis partibus, vt neruis, ſanguine, &amp; membris, vti non potest.</hi> As oure bodies without mindes, ſo a Citie without lawes can not vſe hir partes, as the ſinewes, bloud, with the other members. <hi>Anaxilaus</hi> oftentimes ſayde, that he was the happyeſt Prince, who woulde neuer be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with benefites or giftes. <hi>Micipſa</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in the Hiſtorye of <hi>Saluſt,</hi> that neyther the armie of <hi>Iugurth,</hi> neyther his treaſure, were the munitions of his kingdome, <hi>Sed amici:</hi> who neyther wyth Artillerye can be compelled, or wyth golde are to be purchaſed: but wyth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce and faites are atchieued and wonne. In lyke ſort <hi>Cyrus</hi> by hys owne example inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Croeſus,</hi> as <hi>Xenophon</hi> writeth: While I make my friendes riche, I iudge theſe, my
<pb facs="tcp:16787:18"/>
Iewels and treaſures, yea more faithfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruers of my body, and Realme, than a great garde and fronte of marching ſouldiers. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> wonte to ſaye, that it was not lawfull for any faithfull ſubiect, to departe with ſadde countenaunce from the preſence of the Prince. Wherwith, or the lyke, <hi>Artaxer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes</hi> moued, gaue in rewarde vnto a poore man bringing but a little water in the palme of his hande, and with muche mildeneſſe of ſpeache and countenance receiuing it: a thouſand pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Perſian coyne, with a greate ſtanding goblet of golde. And vnto an other preſenting him with a Pomegranate, he gaue the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a mightye Citie. <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi> ſtill was angrie, for that hys Subiectes aſked nothing of him. <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> was more diſpleaſed wyth them which refuſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, than wyth thoſe which craued giftes at hys handes. And therfore writyng to <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Athens,</hi> ſayth, that he woulde not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compte him his friende, if he did refuſe his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentes and giftes, which he had ſent to <hi>Athens</hi> for his behoofe. I might here blaſe out <hi>Caeſars</hi> paſſing prayſe, who was liberall to al his ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers as wel footemen as horſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in fine to all the whole people of <hi>Rome,</hi> enriching them with the abundance of money, corne, and
<pb facs="tcp:16787:19"/>
oyle, but eſpeciallye to <hi>Seruius Galba,</hi> who ſued in the Senate before him ſaid: <hi>O Caie Iuli Caeſar, pro Pompeio magno, quondam genero tuo, ſpoſpondi.</hi> O <hi>Caius Iulius Caeſar,</hi> for <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, ſomtime thy ſonne in law, I became ſuertie: To whome <hi>Caeſar</hi> wyth gentle gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aunſwered: <hi>Ego te hoc aere liberabo.</hi> I will oute of hande diſcharge thy debt. Whoſe cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie was equall and like to his liberalitie: ſo that <hi>Marius Geminus</hi> not withoute cauſe ſaid: <hi>Caeſar,</hi> thoſe that dare ſpeake before thee, <hi>Magnitudinem tuam ignorant,</hi> are ignorant of thy valiaunt courage: <hi>Qui non audent, humanitatem.</hi> and they which dare not, are inſcient of thy hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manitie. <hi>Scipio</hi> likewiſe was wont to ſaye, that it is better to ouerthrow the enimies with gentleneſſe, than with ſpeare and ſhield. <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> prayſed two things in a Prince: <hi>Amicis benefacere: Inimicos verò ſibi reconciliare.</hi> To wyt, the gratifying of hys friendes, and the recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement of his enimies vnto himſelf. <hi>Antigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> daylie confeſſed, that the good wyll of his Subiects, was the beſt foundation of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the moſte ſureſt ſtay therof. For (as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayeth) <hi>Ferrum tuetur Principem, melius fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Octauia.</note> And agayn: <hi>Decet timeri Caeſarem, aut plus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligi.</hi> Sword doth defend the Prince: but better, fayth. Whome it behoueth to bee feared, but
<pb facs="tcp:16787:19"/>
better to bee loued. Friendſhip therefore, and not flatterye is to be intertayned of a Prince. Than the whyche (as <hi>Aratus</hi> writeth) no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng is more ſtronger, it beyng better by the opinion of <hi>Periander</hi> and <hi>Cyrus</hi> to be forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with friendſhip, than with harneſſed horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Therfore al ſeruile and fawnyng flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers were baniſhed among the Egiptians, and only twenty of the noble Prieſtes ſonnes well learned, hauyng paſſed the .xx. yeare of theyr age, ſtoode alwaye before the King: Through whoſe continual preſence he might be withdra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen from all wicked enterpriſes, and by their paſſing pollicies and cunning knowledge he myght be inſtructed in all Princelye proweſſe. So that (as <hi>Seneca</hi> teacheth) he might dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be buſied in prouiding for his Countrie,<note place="margin">In Octauia.</note> ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring afflicted perſons, abſteyning from <hi>Teu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonical</hi> tiranny and bolde bloudeſhed, gyuing place to wrathe and anger, purchaſing peace and quietneſſe to the world. <hi>Haec ſumma virtus: petitur hac coelu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> via.</hi> This is a Princelye Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, by this pathe is heauen perced, and (as <hi>Virgil</hi> writeth) in ſparing ſubiectes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ene.</hi> 6.</note> and ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing proud perſons. So that by the aſſertions of the Heathen it maye appeare that the office of a King is no payneleſſe Prouince, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together obnoxious to the trauailes of bodye,
<pb facs="tcp:16787:20"/>
and the troubles of mind. And therfore accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mablye the Scripture calleth Kings the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars of <hi>Libanus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 70. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 41. <hi>Exod.</hi> 24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47. <hi>Oſeae.</hi> 4.</note> the heads of the people, the foundations of hilles, wagons, Goddes, the bucklers of the earth, for that they from theyr ſubiectes award al iniuries, euen as with buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and targets, dartes, and deadely blowes be remoued from the bodies of encombaters. The Hebrewes doe call theym the Goates of the earth: for as the Goates goe before the heardes of Kids: ſo do Kings and Princes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the people. The Egyptians do name them <hi>Patres Religionis,</hi> or by ſome tranſlations, <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatores mundi,</hi> Fathers of religion or Sauiours of the world.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 38.</note> The Romaines called their hye Officer <hi>Conſul,</hi> a Counſailer to his Country, and alſo a Father of his Country. The Paleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines called theyr King <hi>Abimelech,</hi> that is to ſaye,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 26.</note> oure Father the Kyng. The Egyptians cleaped theyr Kyng <hi>Pharao,</hi> a reuenger of the languyſhmentes of hys ſubiectes. Chriſt called the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>beneficos,</hi> that is to ſaye, gracious Lords.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> termeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Deacons or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God: <hi>Peter</hi> cleapeth them the chiefe heads or meſſaged rulers of the people. Whoſe duty as hitherto it hathe bene arayed with the peerleſſe Poeſies of Prophane Paynims and Heathen wryters, well exerciſed in Politike
<pb facs="tcp:16787:20"/>
proweſſe: So moſt daintely is it delineated in the holy and ſacred Scriptures, they requyring in him moſt eſpeciallye the feruent feare and dread of God. So that he called to that functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, muſt not multiplie vnto hym ſelfe horſſes, neither bryng backe agayne the people vnto ſtraunge religion, either puffe vp hym ſelfe in the number of Chariottes, and mighty maſſes of ſiluer and gold: but ſittyng on hys ſaet,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.</note> ſhal write or cauſe to be written for his inſtruction in a booke, the preciſe Preſident of the Law of God, receyuing it of the high Prieſtes, which he ſhal diligentlye defray, and reuerently read al his life long, continuallye carying the ſame with him, wherein he may learne to feare the Lord his God, his word and Ceremonies he maye obſerue, eſtranging from his heart all preſumpteous pryde aboue hys brethren. And neither leaning to the ryght or lefte hand, may liue long with al his line.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.</note> Wherefore <hi>Moyſes</hi> to this effect and purpoſe choſe oute wiſe men from the Elders of Iſraell, euen ſuch as feared God, in whome the truth with an immortall hatred of couetouſneſſe was planted. Whoſe politie and experience was openlye knowen.</p>
            <p>Whoſe godly conuerſation was allowed of al the people: accordyng to this ſhort verſe: <hi>Iudex eſto pius, ſapiens, verax, miſodorus.</hi> Wherin firſt of
<pb facs="tcp:16787:21"/>
all, godlyneſſe cauſeth all iudging Princes to reſpect God in all their doings, and to take di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent hede, that they committe no ſuch thing, wherewith he maye take iuſt offence. Wiſdom gouerneth all theyr affections, ſo that by error they may not wander out of the way. Truth burieth all falſe interpretations, and putteth to ſilence al Sicophantes of lawes. The hatred of couetouſneſſe continueth alwayes ſinceritie in iudgement. And as theſe thyngs be incident to a Princely gouernment: ſo moſt chiefly ought he to prouide, that religiouſly, and godlye, and (as the Greke text is) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in omni pietate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; vero cultu Dei viuere poſsint,</hi> in all pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and true worſhipping of God his ſubiectes maye lead their liues. This was commended in <hi>Abraham</hi> by the Aungell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 18.</note> he practiſing the ſame in the Fatherlye gouernement of his ſonnes: beyng muche more laudable in a Prince. Who by aucthoritie, care, primacie, and power, is the common father to al his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes. So that, as <hi>Abraham</hi> gaue commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to his ſonnes: ſo ought a Prince vnto hys ſubiectes <hi>De cuſtodienda via Domini,</hi> of the keping of the way of the Lorde, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, ſhewing him ſelfe a Nurſſe of Gods Church, a ſetter vp of Colleges and ſchooles, in the which a true and liuely knowledge and
<pb facs="tcp:16787:21"/>
inuocation of God with al other neceſſary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline may be preſerued and kept. Whervnto not onely the example of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 18. <hi>Gene.</hi> 28. <hi>Gene.</hi> 39.</note> but moſte eſpecially of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> that noble Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarke and Prince of Egypte, may as a moſt worthye mirror, induce al Chriſtian Princes, of whom the Prophete <hi>Dauid</hi> writeth in this ſort: <hi>Deus miſit ante eos virum: In ſeruum venun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datus est Ioſeph. Miſit Rex, &amp; ſoluit eum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.</note> 
               <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtituit eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dominum domus ſuae, vt erudiret Principes doctrina ſua, &amp; ſenes eius prudentiam doceret.</hi> God ſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Patriarches <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who was ſold into Egypt as a bond ſeruant. For whom the king of Egypte ſent, ſetting hym at freedome and libertie.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 41. <hi>Gene.</hi> 38.</note> He made hym Prince ouer his houſe and kingdome cleaping him the Sauior of the world, and a Father of Religion, that he might inſtructe wyth hys doctrine hys Nobles and Peeres, &amp; might teach hys Senators the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, to wit, the fall of the firſt fathers, preaching vnto them of the ſanctified feede to come of the ingraffed humors of all naturall things, to wete, of the heauenlie influences, of the celeſtial ſignes and Planets, with the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and powers of plantes, and might alſo prepare all neceſſary foode for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> throughout all Egypt, aſwell for body as minde, viſiting all Regions and Cities throughoute al <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raos</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16787:22"/>
Kingdome, ſhewing hym ſelfe bothe a Prince and Byſhop. This appeared in <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> that mighty Magiſtrate,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.</note> who ſettled in the people of Iſraell all true Religion and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhypping of God, which he had immediatlye receyued of hym, preſcribing vnto <hi>Aaron</hi> and all the Leuites, what was to be followed, and alſo what was to be eſchued, ſharply rebuking <hi>Aaron</hi> for his idolatry, and the defiling of the Religion of the God of Iſraell. The lyke may they behold in <hi>Ioſue</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nun,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſuae. <hi>8.</hi> &amp; vltimo. Gene. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> who receyued a commaundement from God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore his Religion firſte deliuered vnto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> to wete, that he might the ſeconde time circumcyſe the chyldren of Iſrael (for Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was a pledge of Gods couenant.) altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpecting Gods Religion, at whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement the Arke of God was caried of the Prieſtes, aultars were buylded, the people were ſanctified, ſtraunge Gods were abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, a truce betwene God and the people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, the worde of the League in the Lawe of God indited, and a title as a witneſſe thereof was by hym erected. And who knoweth not, that King Dauid brought home agayne the Arke of God, whyth was negligently ſuffered to remayne amongſt the Heathen by the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Paral.</hi> 13.</note> and Kyng Saule, reſtoring the Religion
<pb facs="tcp:16787:22"/>
of God, appointyng Prieſtes and Leuites the ſingyng of Pſalmes and Hymnes by courſe. Who is ignorant of <hi>Salomons</hi> zeale in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Temple of GOD?<note place="margin">2. <hi>Paral.</hi> 6. 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8</note> at whoſe dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he made an excellent Oration of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping vnto the people, remouing <hi>Abiathar</hi> from his Biſhopricke, and placing <hi>Sadoch</hi> in his rowme. Whoſe eares hath not the fame of Kyng <hi>Aſa</hi> pierced, Kyng of <hi>Iuda,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed all Idolles in the land of <hi>Iuda, Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> and <hi>Ephraim,</hi> building an Aultare vnto the Lord? What Countrie doeth not reuerence the Religion of <hi>Ioſaphat,</hi> who deſtroyed the hyll aultars and groues in <hi>Iuda,</hi> and ſent the Princelieſt perſons of hys Kyngdome wyth Prieſtes and Leuites to teache all the Cities in <hi>Iuda: <hi>Habentesue librum legis Domini,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Para.</hi> 17</note> 
               <hi>circui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, atque erudiebant populum.</hi> And hauing the booke of the Lawe of God, trauailed rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute, and taught the people both in <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> To whom is <hi>Ezechias</hi> earneſty vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Para.</hi> 29.</note> who purged the Temple of all Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Reliques, burning lightes therein,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18. 4. <hi>Reg</hi> 23. 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 12. 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng ſweete perfumes, breaking the braſen ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pent, and puttinp it to pouder. I nede not make mention of <hi>Ioſias, Iehu,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ioas,</hi> who ſtil warned the Prieſts of their duty, reſtrained their riot and inſolency, and laſt of all deliuered to death
<pb facs="tcp:16787:23"/>
the falſe and peruerſe Prophetes. But what do I (as the Latine prouerbe ſayth) lyght a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to helpe the moſte glorious beames of the ſhinyng Sunne? Thys not onelye in the time of ſhadowes, but alſo in the time of grace and truth, hath moſt plainely appeared. As of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> we reade,<note place="margin">Euſeb. li. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> in promoting the Religion of God in the Counſel of <hi>Nice:</hi> of <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> the firſte, at the Counſell of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople: Theodoſius</hi> the ſecond, at the Counſell of <hi>Epheſus:</hi> and to be ſhort, of <hi>Martianus,</hi> at the Counſell of <hi>Calcedon.</hi> Who ſhewed them ſelues the true and naturall Nurſſes of Gods Church, and the foſtering fathers of Chriſt his Religion, according to the ſaying of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſay:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 44.</note> 
               <hi>Reges erunt Nutritij tui.</hi> Kings ſhal be thy feeders and foſterers. Makyng this the chiefe care amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the muſters of their though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to conforme their will to the will of God, to ſet forth his holye worde, to direct all things to his honor and glory, and to make hym in all things both theyr beginning and ending, fullye aunſwering the definition of S. Paule:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Dei enim Miniſter eſt tibi in bonum.</hi> For he is the Miniſter of God for thy wealth. Which is not onely extended to the bodye, but alſo to the ſoule. Foraſmuche as man is compoſed
<pb facs="tcp:16787:23"/>
of theſe two principall partes, who lyueth not onely by bread a bodilie life, but alſo a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all lyfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. <hi>Math.</hi> 4. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. <hi>Io.</hi> 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> euen by euery worde proceeding out of the mouth of God, which is ſpirite and lyfe, which is the power of God, working ſaluation in the beleuers, mollifying their heartes, and perfectly cleanſing them. For the which Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces continually ought to care, as the Greke text teacheth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in hoc ipſum conſtanter ac perſeueranter incumbentes ac immorantes.</hi> they vnceſſantly preſt to be occupied &amp; buſied in propaling the pure Religion &amp; true worſhipping of God: according to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaying of <hi>S. Auguſtine: <hi>In hoc Reges ſeruiunt Deo,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> ad Chryſ.</note> 
               <hi>ſi in regno ſuo bona iubeant, mala ꝓhibeant: non ſolùm quae per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent ad ſocietate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> humanam, ſed quae ad Religionem diuinam.</hi> In this Kings doe ſeruice vnto God, if they in their Kingdomes commaunde good things, and forbid euill, not only appertaining to humaine ſocietie, but alſo to the Religion of God. Authorizing Godly and learned perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the ſuperintendment and Miniſterie of the Churche, eſtranging from thence Drones and time ſlaues, Almon eaters,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg</hi> 13. <hi>Io.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Ieroboams</hi> Prieſts, and Barly bread Goſpellers, foreclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing loſe liuers and ſeducers by leauened doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, maintayning peace and concord among them, keeping a continuall watche, that the
<pb facs="tcp:16787:24"/>
worde of life &amp; ſalvation may be faithfully and purelye preached without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſerable mixture of humaine traditions,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Luc.</hi> 16.</note> which make of no force y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of God, they beyng abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation vnto the Lorde, although (greatly eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of men,) vtterly deceiuing them, who are the firſt finders out therof, according to the teſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>timony of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet <hi>Eſay:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 47.</note> 
               <hi>Sapientia tua &amp; ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia tua, ea ipſa decepit te. Defeciſti in multitudine adinuentionum tuarum.</hi> Thy wiſedome, and thy ſkill, euen the ſelfe ſame hath deceyued thee. Thou haſte ſoultred in the multitude of thine owne inuentions, wherein God taketh no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. For he regardeth not fleſh and bloud. He weyeth not outward ſignes &amp; ſilly ceremonies, neither wil he be worſhipped in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but in the ſpirite of truth by Chriſte Ieſus. For he is a buſy beholder of faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.</note> conſidering the inwarde intent, being a ſubtile ſearcher of hidde hearts. Theſe things not promoting vs to God, with whom nothing is attentiuely accepted beſide a firme faith in Chriſt: theſe did <hi>Plato</hi> remoue from the worſhippyng of the highe God, for the which he was called, <hi>Diuinus Plato.</hi> Theſe did Chriſt vtterly put to flight, when as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared all things to be fully ended, which were neceſſarie for mans ſaluation, not faſtening his Church to the bondage of figures, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16787:24"/>
freedome of the ſpirit. A Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prince there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt (all trifeling traditions ſette a part, and the ydle inuentions of mortall men) direct his ſubiectes vnto the Law and teſtimonies of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 8.34.</note> to make diligent ſearch in the booke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, and to reade therein, to ſhewe vnto them that which is expreſſed in the Scripture of trueth, to cauſe them to heare <hi>Moyſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. <hi>Luc.</hi> 16. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5. <hi>Act.</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.13.</note> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophets, earneſtly to exhort them to reade the Scriptures, which beare witneſſe of Chriſt and of his power, which fittingly ſhewe forth hys dayes, and that eternall lyfe and health ſettled in him. Whiche thing if it had bene practiſed in all ages of all Chriſtian Princes, poyſon had neuer bene ſhedde in the Church.<note place="margin">De praeſcrip. Haeret.</note> Then the bleſſed Church (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, and the moſt ſimplieſt, as <hi>Damaſcius</hi> writeth to <hi>Ierom</hi>) had neuer receyued any mans doctrine againſt the doctrine and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Chriſte. Then had not Religion brought and chylded forth that Cocatrice egge (Riches) neyther ſhould the daughter haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother. Then had neuer the Kings of the earth willingly dronke the cup of ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Circes,</hi> &amp; wittingly haue ben empoiſoned therewith. The diſcipline of the Apoſtles (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> writeth) had neuer by idleneſſe,<note place="margin">De lapſis.</note> and the want of Chriſtes Croſſe, bene corrupted,
<pb facs="tcp:16787:25"/>
and by heaping of Patrimonie, generally for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. Then palpable darkeneſſe had neuer been receyued in the place of cleare and large light:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 5.</note> when as (as the Scripture witneſſeth) the Prophetes preached lyes, and the Prieſtes allowed the ſame by clappyng their handes, and the people loued ſuch ſeruice. Then ſhould neuer Gods ſiluer haue ben turned into droſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1.</note> Then ſhoulde the Citie which in times paſte was faithful, not haue bene proſtituted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, to wit, the chaſt Churche of God, vnder the maſke of a haunted harlot. Then ſhoulde neuer the houſe of God, whiche by inſtitution is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 21. <hi>Luc.</hi> 19. <hi>Math.</hi> 24. 2. <hi>Theſs.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the houſe of true worſhippe and religion, haue bene made a houſe of fooliſh fables. Then deſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as Chriſt ſaith) ſhould neuer haue ſtoode in holie place, nor Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt haue pitched his pauilion in the Temple of God, lying Legendes and Maſters of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, had neuer taken place in the Church of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>21.</hi> Luc. <hi>21. 3.</hi> lib. Ep. <hi>3.</hi> ad Ce.</note> Then had not the Sunne nor Moone loſt their light, and the ſtarres haue fallen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith) <hi>Vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> lex Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelica, &amp; traditio dominica ſeruata fuiſſet.</hi> The law of the Goſpel, and the traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Lord had ſtill bene retinued euery where and from it which Chriſt taught, there had bene no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture nor reuoltment, and al other doctrines
<pb facs="tcp:16787:25"/>
(as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writeth) had bene iudged dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, and to bee defied,<note place="margin">Offic. <hi>1.</hi> de vir. vel. <hi>4.</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per. <hi>1.</hi> ad Co. Super vlt. Cap. ad Ro.</note> yea (as <hi>Theophila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus</hi> witneſſeth) had bene accompted hereſie, ſtumbling blocks and diſſentions. To be ſhort, then neuer ſuch calamities had happened, and confuſion of truth whereby the verye electe of God (if it had bene poſſible) ſhoulde haue bene allured to ignorance the mother of error,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 24.</note> euen of the Scriptures, as <hi>Ierom</hi> writeth,<note place="margin">Prolog. ſup. Iſaiam.</note> which is the ignoraunce of Chriſt. And I would to God that Princes in theſe daies would conſider the neceſſitie hereof, eſpeciallye thoſe, who boaſte moſt of the reformation of Religion. Then woulde they not be afraide boldly to enter into the Churche, and whyp buyers and ſellers out of the Temple of God, not ſuffering the Lords Pigeons to bee ſolde therin: pulling vp by the rootes euery plant which the heauenly Father hath not planted.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.</note> Then woulde they burſt out into theſe ſemblants of wordes: Holyneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.</note> O Lorde, becommeth thine houſe for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. The zeale of thy houſe hath deuoured me vp.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.</note> Then would they commaund ſuperſtitious Ceremonies euen wyth the earneſtie and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous affection of Chriſte to be done awaye: <hi>Auferte ista hinc,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; nolite facere domum patris mei domum negotiationis.</hi> Away wyth bag and bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, wyth all your traſhe and trumpery, and
<pb facs="tcp:16787:26"/>
make not my fathers houſe a houſe of traffike: leaſt that plague followe which the Prophete threateneth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Regnum quod non ſeruierit Chriſto, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribit.</hi> That Kingdome whych ſhall not ſerue Chriſt, ſhal come to deadly downefall. So that as fyrſt the Prince ought to caſt his chiefe care vpon doctrine: ſo ſecondly, with the like conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration ought he to regard the Sacramentes inſtituted by Chriſte, and the adminiſtration therof according to his inſtitution. Wherin he may folow <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> with diuers others, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing vnto them by a generalitye of facte, comely ryghtes: but in ſpecialitie of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance leauyng them indifferent, cutting of noyfull and ſuperfluous Ceremonies, ſequeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring them which euidently ſtruggle with the worde of God, euen ſuch, whoſe worke and vſe are not free. But theſe thyngs put in vre of a Prince, he muſt not ſo ceaſſe, nay to the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of all righteouſneſſe, he muſte retayne the ſeueritie of Lawes, chaſtening by them, as it were the rod of diſcipline. For then (as <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> writeth) <hi>Summus locus bene regitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Lib. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralium.</note> 
               <hi>cùm Principes vitiis potius quàm ſubditis dominantur.</hi> The Princelye place is well furnyſhed, when as rather vices than Subiectes be kept vnder, and tamed: The which place (as <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> teacheth) <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanguini debetur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Policrat.</note> 
               <hi>ſed meritis. Et inuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter
<pb facs="tcp:16787:26"/>
regnat, qui rex naſcitur, &amp; non meretur.</hi> Is not due to byrth, but to merits. And he vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ruleth which is borne a King, and by noble proweſſe deſerueth not the ſame. So that they may vnder him lead an honeſt &amp; godly life, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration had, that they be not the children of the night, but of the day: not of darkeneſſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſs.</hi> 5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 50.13. <hi>Rom.</hi>
               </note> but of the light, and therefore accordinglie preaſt to walke. Yea he muſte cut of all corruption of maners, all laſciuiouſneſſe, all vnchaſte ſongs, all vnfitting attire, al ſurfetting and dronken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, all whoredome and wantonneſſe, all fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned profeſſion of chaſtitie without a continuall continencie both of minde and body, he beeyng firſt of all, a myrrour to his ſubiects in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature and moderation of dyet, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt chiefly Kingdomes be bleſſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 29. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>Cùm Principes veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur in tempore ſuo ad reficiendum, &amp; non ad lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xuriam.</hi> When Princes doe feede in due ſeaſon to refreſh &amp; ſuſtaine their weake bodyes, and not pamper vp to lothſome luſtes. And as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> ſayth:<note place="margin">In ſuis exhor.</note> 
               <hi>Illud Regnum in gradu aeterno facilè ſteterit, vbi minimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> virium Veneris cupido ſibi ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicauerit.</hi> That Kingdome ſhall ſtande in ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt eſtate, where as <hi>Venus</hi> retinue ſhall haue leaſt acceſſe. Wherefore the Kings of Egipte vſed very precyſe dyet, drinking a ſmall quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of Wyne, feeding onely vpon Heale and
<pb facs="tcp:16787:27"/>
Gooſe, to the ende that by their example theyr Subiects likewiſe might be allured therevnto. For vainlie do Princes redreſſe maners, when as firſt of all the ſaturitie of breade, gluttonie, ſurfetting, is not ſurpryſed and layde in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Of which and like enormious crimes, all Princes ſhal giue a ſtrayght accompt vnto the dreadfull Iudge both of the quicke &amp; the deade, when as no priuileges nor charters ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to excuſe them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 24. <hi>Sop.</hi> 1. <hi>Sap.</hi> 6. <hi>Iob.</hi> 7.15.12.34. <hi>Amos.</hi> 9.</note> who ſhall ſearch both their wordes and their workes. <hi>Et potentes potenter tormenta patientur.</hi> And pourable perſons ſhall ſuffer paſſing puniſhments, yea the Lords eies be vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuche, <hi>&amp; conteret illos à facie terrae.</hi> And he ſhall roote the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth. For they be as S. Paule calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>vltores ad ira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reuengers of malefactors,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> they bearing not a ſworde in vaine. Holding one to be awarded againſt his Subiectes, and an other to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced againſt the forren enimy. The firſt is called the ſworde of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wherewith the euill members are cut of. The ſecond is called the ſworde of warre, tendered againſt the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rener, whereby publike peace, equitie, &amp; quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe may be by hym obtayned for his ſubiects, he being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſter of God vnto their behouf and wealth, for the which S. Paule teacheth that they do pay tribute, wherof there are three
<pb facs="tcp:16787:27"/>
eſpecial reſpectes &amp; laudable endes, to wit, that they ſhould be orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of peace,<note place="margin">Cicero pro leg. Manili.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſidies of warre, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knitting ſinnowes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like weale. But here eſpecially let Princes take hede, that no ſuch talenges be leuied on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to ſerue, as inſtruments, their priuat luſts and ryotous lyfe. Let them alſo further vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, as <hi>Xenophon</hi> warned renoumed King <hi>Cyrus,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Regula Regis non affectus, ſed lex eſſe debet.</hi> Not the will or affection of the Prince, but the lawe oughte to be a rule vnto him in gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which giueth them no intereſt or right in the occupying &amp; poſſeſſion of their ſubiects goods, but as they may be applyed for defence &amp; munition ſake, wherewith vnder them quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they may be gouerned, for the atchieuement whereof, as ſubiects ought to pray,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> ſo Princes ought to vſe greate pollicie and care: not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a continuall furniſhing of their Realmes with certaine ordinarie bandes and frontires of men, but alſo in maintayning Nauigation and Ships vnto the Sea, ſtrengthning Forts &amp; Blockhouſes, repayring ruinous Rodes, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and landing places, both for trafficke and ſafegarde ſake, rayſing vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> walles of decayed Cities, marching towardes the enimie, forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the ſame wyth artillery, prouiding for
<pb facs="tcp:16787:28"/>
warre in time of peace, weighing in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of reaſon, that be there neuer ſo great a calme, as great a flaw and ſtorme doth follow: yea neuer ſo high a hill, but there is as lowe a dale &amp; valley. Wherefore <hi>Salomon</hi> is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in holy writ, and ſo alſo is King <hi>Aſa</hi> in the Scriptures. Whoſe examples all other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ought to imitate and follow ſuch exploits and trauelles, being worthie for their perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 32.</note> according to the teſtimonie of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſay: <hi>Princeps ea quae ſunt digna Principe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitabit, &amp; ipſe ſuper duces ſtabit.</hi>
               </hi> A Prince ſhall reſpect thoſe things which be ſitting for hys eſtate, &amp; he ſhal guide &amp; order the enterpriſes of his captaines. Whoſe maieſtie and authoritie is the only gift of God, whoſe lucky ſucceſſe in battaile commeth from the Lorde of Hoſtes, whoſe reuerence, loue, and loyaltie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, iſſueth from Gods ſpirite, according to the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Salomon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>Vt oculus videat, &amp; auris audiat, Dominus facit vtrum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</hi> That the eye ſhould ſee, and the eare heare, the Lord bringeth both to paſſe. Which we may behold in the Patriarch <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> Whome God made to excell in wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to foreſee that famine to come, to remedy that preſent miſchiefe: to be ſhort, that the eare of <hi>Pharao</hi> with al the Egyptians ſhould heare this yong man being a priſoner, and ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:16787:28"/>
alſo obey his motions, it was the onely bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of God. The like is to be ſayd of <hi>Themi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocles,</hi> in whome God maruellouſly brought to paſſe, that he ſhould through counſell pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle, weighing how warre was to be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dered againſt <hi>Xerxes,</hi> commending his policies vnto the Grecians, who willingly ſhould obey and receyue the ſame. Vnto theſe muſt a Prince wyſhe good ſucceſſe, according to the deſier of <hi>Aeſchylus:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Post Conſilium ſequatur obedientia &amp; ſucceſsus.</hi> After aduiſement lette obedience conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow in the Subiects, and in the feates of chiualrie good ſucceſſe, ſo that the common A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſme may take place: <hi>Par ſit fortuna labori.</hi> Let Fortune aunſwere trauayle and toyle. So ſhall his Kingdome proſper &amp; floriſh, his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhalbe ſpread throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world, his noble conqueſtes to immortalitie ſhall be commended, his Princely ofſpring ſhall neuer fayle, he ſhall be bleſſed in the length of dayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.62.</note> the multitude of people, with obedient and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſubiects, and in the aboundance of all good and profitable things.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Da.</hi> 9.</note> So ſhould all plagues and famines be farre eſtraunged from him, the confuſion of face and familie arrefte, the feare of forren enimie farre forecloſed, hauing all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes before his eyes this ſhort verſe, writing
<pb facs="tcp:16787:29"/>
the ſame in the ſupplied table of his heart. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Principium &amp; finem in omnibus facito Deum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Para.</hi> 16.</note> In all thinges make God thy begynning and ending, in him onely put thou thy truſte, and not in other Princes, who placeth Princes in their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne ſeates,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Da.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 4. <hi>Pro.</hi> 8. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 32. <hi>Iob.</hi> 36.41.</note> and there confirmeth them for euer, by whome Kings doe rule, and Lawegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers yelde iuſt ſentence, hauing dominion in all Kingdomes, and on whom he wil, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth them. To whom euen God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the holy Ghoſt, three diſtinct perſons, and one immortall and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God, be all honor, glorie, and prayſe worlde wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>JMPRINTED AT London by H. Denham. Anno. <hi>1566.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16787:29"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
